<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirror of diuine prouidence Containing a collection of Theodoret his arguments: declaring the prouidence of God to appeare notably both in the heauens and in the earth, and in all things therein contained: taken out of his workes De prouidentia.</title>
            <title>De providentia. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Theodoret, Bishop of Cyrrhus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1039:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirror of diuine prouidence Containing a collection of Theodoret his arguments: declaring the prouidence of God to appeare notably both in the heauens and in the earth, and in all things therein contained: taken out of his workes De prouidentia.</title>
                  <title>De providentia. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Theodoret, Bishop of Cyrrhus.</author>
                  <author>I. C., fl. 1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. C[reede] for Iohn Smithick, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstons churchyard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of selections of Theodoret.  De providentia.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: I.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MIRROR of Diuine <hi>Prouidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing a collection of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> his arguments: declaring the Prouidence of God to appeare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably both in the heauens and in the earth, and in all things therein contained: Taken out of his workes <hi>De Prouidentia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by T.C. for Iohn Smithick, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. Dunſtons Churchyard in Fleetſtreet. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2139:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2139:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He copie of this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection hauing long ſince lyen by mee, I haue now thought good to publiſh, as a worke well worthy to be read and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſed of all ſorts of people, at this time, wherein Atheiſme like an ill weed, is growne to ſuch height, as it ſeemeth to ouerſhadow the plants of true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, while men attributing to Nature, what belongs properly to the Creator of Nature, do both depriue God of his glory, and alſo diſcouer their impiety, to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their owne ſoules, and the hurt of others. The matter was originally handled by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> an auncient and learned Father of the Church, in tenne Sermons, treating of Prouidence, the ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:2139:3"/>whereof hath bene extracted, and digeſted into Method by a learned Diuine, now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, who made this Collection follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Read it with aduiſe; and if thou dooſt beleeue the <hi>Diuine Prouidence,</hi> as thou oughteſt, the meditation thereof may bee ſweet &amp; comfortable vnto thee: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou doubt, or denie it, the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof may ſtrike thee with ſhame and terror, and haply reclaime thee from ſo abſurd and impious an opinion: which ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect I do heartily wiſh, that it may worke in thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2139:3"/>
            <head>THE MIRROR <hi>of Diuine Prouidence.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cauſes why he defendeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God against the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous mouthes, that denie the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defend their Parents.
<note place="margin">Reaſons why.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Seruaunts their Maiſters.</p>
               <p>Citizens theyr Cities.</p>
               <p>The gard their Prince.</p>
               <p>Much more ought Chriſtians to defend Gods cauſe.</p>
               <p>For God is nearer vnto vs then our Fathers,
<note place="margin">Reaſons of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> by whoſe benefite they be made parents.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2139:4"/>
               <p>He is better then our maiſters, (whoſe rule is by nature, not by the calamitie of the ſeruants).</p>
               <p>He is ſtronger then any wall of braſſe, as he, whom no time can weare away, nor force impaire.</p>
               <p>Hee is more princely then any king, whoſe rule is perpetuall, and ouer all.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Prouidence of God is prooued in the Heauens.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt,
<note place="margin">Nature.</note> in that the heauens being of a paſſible &amp; corruptible na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, notwithſtanding continue vntil this day whole and perfit, in an vniform order,
<note place="margin">Order. Motion.</note> or motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption, by the onely word of the Creator.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they being ſo neare the Sunne, Moone and Starres, (which by nature be fierie), for all that are neither melted, dried,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2139:4"/>nor ſet on fire after ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>It is proued alſo in the Sunne.</head>
                  <p>THe Sunne contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (for that all fire is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpward) doth caſt downe his beames and heate towardes the earth. Likewiſe the water, being by nature fluxible and heauie, is carried vpward, and hangeth in the aire, without any ſtaie.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the Sunne is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to giue light to all creatures.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">The vſe of the Sunne.</note> it ſerues for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of time: for the Sunne by riſing and ſetting, doth diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the night, which is the meaſure of all time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Night is as neceſſarie as the day.</head>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2139:5"/>
                  <p>FIrſt, by the night the light bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interrupted, the day is made more pleaſant in his ſecond comming.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the bodies beeing wearied with the day labour, and by ſleepe, bed, and reſt, well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, are made apt again to the next dayes labour.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it giueth to the wilde beaſts a free and ſafe opportunitie to ſeeke their pray.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, and laſt of all, the daies thereby being meaſured, it is conſequently the true meaſure of all time:
<note place="margin">The proofe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> for by the night, daies are meaſured: by dayes, the weekes: by weekes, the moneths: by moneths, the yeares. And ſo it is the meaſure of all time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2139:5"/>
                  <head>Againe, the Prouidence is prooued by the foure parts of the yeare.</head>
                  <p>IN that God hath not ioyned the Winter and Sommer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (which are extreames) but hath placed betweene them, the Spring and Autumne, as meanes to qualifie their extremities, to the comfort and preſeruation of all creatures: for in comming by litle, and litle, as by degrees from the extremitie of cold, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of heat, we are both in leſſe daunger, &amp; receiue the more pleaſure: for the ſudden, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great alteration from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame to an other, is very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto nature.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as theſe foure parts of the yeare are prouidently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ſo are they all neceſſary. The Winter to ſowe, the Spring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2139:6"/>to growe, the Sommer to ripen, the Autumne to reape, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Laſt of all he gathereth the Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence by the Starres alſo.</head>
                  <p>FOr the Starres, beſide their light, are ordained as guides to direct Marriners ſayling vpon the ſeas, where there is no tracke of Horſe, Moyle, wheele, or wayfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A demonſtration of the Prouidence by the Aire, Earth, Sea, Riuers, and Fountaines.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>By the Aire.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, whereas it is by nature fluxible, &amp; hath need of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to containe it, God hath ſo placed it betweene heauen and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2139:6"/>earth, as between two moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g walles, that it cannot break forth, but is kept in, to the preſeruation of al liuing creatures, by the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherof all that haue ſence do liue.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, being moued with the watry clouds, it doth moiſten the Earth.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it is as it were a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot to bring the light of the Sunne vnto our eyes.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, beeing placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sunne, and the Earth, it doth with his naturall moiſture and coldneſſe, ſo temper the dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and heate of the Sunne, that wee receiue his light, without griefe, or hurt vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>And leaſt we ſhould imagine the Aire to be the chiefe cauſe of this ſo great benefite, God hath appointed the Sunne likewiſe to temper the extremitie thereof;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2139:7"/>for were it not that the Sun with his beames did warme the Ayre, we were not able to abide the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of his colde, as we may perceiue by the winter, when the Sunne goeth further from vs.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, heereby is the Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence declared, for that the Ayre and Sunne, beeing in their owne natures hurtfull (the one through the extremitie of his cold, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon of his extreame heat) are by the only prouidence of God ſo aptly diſpoſed, that they turne to our great commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, neither in the Sunne, Ayre, nor any one of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeuerally, nor yet in them all ioyntly, dooth the life of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or the encreaſe of the Earth conſiſt. For when the Ayre is moſt temperate, and the Earth watred with ſeaſonable ſhowers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2139:7"/>the Sunne likewiſe vſeth a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the windes do blowe moſt mildely; yea, although the Husbandman plow neuer ſo skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſow in good meaſure, and time, yet doth not the Earth alwaies yeeld her (looked for) fruit liberally: neither is mankind alwaies free from ſickneſſe &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Whereby God ſheweth all things to bee ruled by his Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and not by Nature.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, by the Prouidence of God, the Ayre is ſo preſerued, that although all liuing creatures haue breathed it ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares: yet is it not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or leſſe then it was at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In the Earth.</head>
                  <p>VVHoſe diuers forme (for God hath not made it altogether plaine, neither ſteepe, nor rough
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2139:8"/>altogether, but hath diuided it into hilles, plaine fields, and thick woods) maketh it pleaſant to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and doth delight through her varietie.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the commoditie is great, whileſt the hills being drai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the valleis, do miniſter ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer paſſage in Winter, and yeeld reliefe vnto cattell. Againe, the plain fields in Sommer, are more pleaſant to both purpoſes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, as the hilles &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines doo yeeld matter for Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters, and other Artificers to worke vpon: So the plaine fields doo miniſter plentie of Corne, wherof they ſtand in need: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Prouidence of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the mutuall helpe, and releeuing one of another.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, as God by his Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath enriched the Earth: ſo doth he preſerue and encreaſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2139:8"/>the ſame, that notwithſtanding men haue reaped thereout, great and infinite treaſures: yet is not the ſtore conſumed in ſo many thouſand yeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In Riuers.</head>
                  <p>WHich by the onely Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, doo ebbe, and flowe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In Fountaines, and Springs.</head>
                  <p>WHich by the ſame Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doo oftentimes breake out in the top of very high mountaines, whereas naturally they are carried downward, and by ſinking of deepe pits, wee are compelled to drawe vp the water to our vſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, hee doth not onely by his Prouidence carrie the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2139:9"/>contrary to their nature, vp to the top of mountains, but cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo to hang in the midſt of the Ayre, without any ſtay.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, wheras naturally wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is cold, hee doth warme it in the bowells of the Earth, without fire, to the great profit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of all men, as may be ſeen in the hotte Springs.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Of the which hot Springs, or Bathes, there are of diuerſe kindes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations. viz. 
<list>
                           <item>Some are good to looſen, and mollifie the ſinowes, which are ſtiff throgh cold.</item>
                           <item>Otherſome doo binde againe thoſe which are looſe, &amp; make them ſtrong.</item>
                           <item>Againe, other are good to cut away fleame.</item>
                           <item>Some doo purge melancholy.</item>
                           <item>Otherſome do dry vp ſores &amp; biles, &amp;c.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2139:9"/>
                  <p>All which diuerſities, declare the Prouidence of God, to the comfort &amp; reliefe of vs vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creatures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The abſurditie and impietie of their opinion whith deny the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God.</head>
                  <p>IF God hath no care of thoſe things he hath created, it is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he is not able, or for that he will not.</p>
                  <p>To ſay ſay God is not able (who by his onely word hath created the whole world, &amp; all that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is, in an order, and beautie ſo wonderfull, and vnſpeakeable) beſide the impietie, it is an ouer great abſurditie, conſidering that it is (infinitely) more eaſie to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them being made, then to create them when they were not, and to make them of nothing.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2139:10"/>
                  <p>Againe, to thinke that God doth hate his worke, through en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie or diſdain, thoſe things which hee hath in ſuch an vnſpeakable excellencie created (as that in the written veritie with a great liking he ſaid <hi>(They were all good)</hi> it is an abſurd and blaſphemous impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for no ſuch wickedneſſe can come neare vnto God, who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together good, and goodneſſe it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Againe, for what cauſe ſhould God enuie the world, whether for the greatneſſe thereof, or for the beautie? God being vncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and infinite, who neuer had beginning, &amp; ſhall haue no ende, comprehending all things, is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and comprehended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of nothing; in whoſe hand are all the endes of the worlde, who meaſureth the heauens with his ſpanne, and the whole earth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2139:10"/>with his fiſt, how can he enuie the greatnes of the world, which being compared to him is not an handfull?</p>
                  <p>As for the beautie thereof, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath both that &amp; his whole beeing of God, there is no cauſe of enuie, but rather great cauſe for God to glorie in the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his creatures. For if the moſt enuious man, doth not hate the houſe, and building which hee hath made, becauſe it doth excell in beautie, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooth greatly boaſt, and is proud of the ſame: Much leſſe ought we to thinke that God, in whom there is no enuie, or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, can enuie the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his creation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2139:11"/>
                  <head>The Prouidence of God in the Seas.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, in that God created there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and doth preſerue for the vſe of man, infinit ſtore of diuerſe kindes of fiſhes.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by his onely Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it is kept within his bounds, and dare not paſſe his preſcribed limits; as may appeare by the waues of the Sea, which beeing carried with violence againſt the ſand on the ſhore, do retire again, as it were repenting their fact in preſuming ſo boldly, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of their prefixed bounds.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the Sea is as it were a mediator to knit together in friendſhip, Countries that are farre diſtant one from an other: for God hath not giuen to any one countrie all things neceſſary,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2139:11"/>but hath as it were diuided his benefites, to the intent that one Countrie ſtanding in need of an other, they ſhould all liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in mutuall amitie and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Wherefore the Sea ſerueth to the eaſier tranſporting of that which we can ſpare, and to bring in ſuch commodities as wee doo want, which by cart, and horſes, cannot be done ſo ſpeedily, and with ſo great eaſe: for the burden of one Ship will ſcarce be carried vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thouſand horſes or Camels backes.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, leaſt men ſhould be ouertoyled with long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous trauell, God hath placed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Ilands in the middeſt of the Sea, to be as it were Innes, to reſt their wearied bodies, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets to prouide ſuch neceſſaries as they ſhall need.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2139:12"/>
                  <head>A briefe collection of his arguments, declaring the Prouidence of God through all the parts of the earth.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt the great benefites which wee receiue by the Sea, the Earth, the Aire, &amp; Sun, do plainly declare the fatherly Prouidence of God towards mankind.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it doth appeare in that wonderfull conſtruction of the heauens, which hang ouer our heads.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly in the tribute, that the Earth &amp; other parts of the world do pay yearly &amp; daily to man: for God hath made them as it were ſeruants to man. The Sun to giue light, to warme, and to ripen the fruites of the Earth. The Moone to ſhine in the night ſeaſon. The Starres to guide vs in the darke, to declare the courſe of times, and to direct thoſe which ſaile on the ſea. The Aire being drawne in of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2139:12"/>men, dooth refreſh the naturall heate within. The Raine doth nouriſh, and make the fruite to growe. The Froſt, firſt doth ſtaie the plants and other fruites of the Earth, that they doo not ſpring forth before their time, and doth driue the naturall heate vnto the roote. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly it killeth wormes, which are hurtfull to the fruites. And laſtly, it doth yeeld vnto vs great ſtore of fowle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A demonſtration of the Prouidence in the framing of the Bodie of man.</head>
               <p>WHere (firſt of all) God hauing giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mouth vnto man, to ſet forth the glorie of God, and to giue thanks for the great benefits receiued at his hand: it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme wickednes to abuſe &amp; pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute that noble inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out blaſphemous ſpeeches againſt the Prouidence of God.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2139:13"/>
                  <head>The Mouth and other inſtruments of ſpeech.</head>
                  <p>THe Mouth (which alone doth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare both the wiſedome and great goodnes of God towards man) may well be likened to the muſicall Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which beeing made of bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen pipes, blowne vp with bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, or the breath of man, and mooued with the fingers of him that playeth thereon, doth giue a ſweet and pleaſant ſound: ſo in man, the lungs are as it were the bellowes, which beeing drawne together, and opened againe by the meanes of certaine muſcles, doth ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forth the breath throgh the windpipe, whereby the couer of the throate being opened, it is carried into the Mouth, where Reaſon (which is a ſpeciall gift of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2139:13"/>God in man) by the helpe of the tongue, as with his hand, dooth carrie that breath vnto the teeth, (which are as it were brazen pipes) that it may runne vp and downe, and learne to ſlide eaſily without combrance, and leaſt the tongue through his continuall motion, ſhould wax drie (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the facilitie in his moouing ſhould bee hindered) God hath annexed vnto it a certain kernell, running (as it were a fountaine) with continuall moyſture.</p>
                  <p>Thus Reaſon (which is in man) carrying his purpoſe, and by help of the tongue, beating it againſt the teeth, through the drawing together of the lips, and an apt beating of the Ayre with the breath, that is ſent out of the mouth, this articular voyce is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and made.</p>
                  <p>Againe (whereas the Heart
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2139:14"/>being the fountaine of naturall heat, from whence all the parts of the body drawe their warmth, hath need of ſome cooling and refreſhing) the Lungs drawing impure and freſh ayre, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it vnto the heart, do receiue and take away the other, which was ouer-boyled by reaſon of the heat of the Hart, and expell it as ſuperfluous and hurtfull; and ſo that breath and ayre which is caſt out as a thing ſuperfluous, and to no vſe, is by the Prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God turned to this notable vſe, to be the author and worker of our ſpeech.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Heart.</head>
                  <p>THe Heart (beeing the moſt excellent part of mans body, hauing as it were the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole committed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2139:14"/>vnto him) by the Prouidence of God is ſo encloſed, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the breſt, as with a moſt ſtrong bulwark, that no outward force can lightly hurt it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the Heart beeing in continuall motion (for it is the fountaine of the Arteries) the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part (vnder which the Lungs are placed) is ſoft, ſpungie, full of Pores and Arteries, but the vpper tip thereof, God hath made more ſtiffe, and hath couered it with a ſtrong and tough coate of skinne.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for that the Heart is nouriſhed, not onely with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſpirits, but alſo with bloud, God hath placed a great hollow veine going through the whole body, whereby it doth drawe his nutriment from the Liuer, as through a conduit pipe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2139:15"/>
               <head>The meanes &amp; Inſtruments wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the body is nouriſhed.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Belly.</head>
                  <p>THe Belly with the helpe of the ſtomacke, doth draw the meate downe vnto it, where firſt keeping it, and drawing out the moyſture, altering and changing it; afterwards, when it is well ſod and digeſted, he doth ſeuer and diſtribute it, ſending the purer part thereof vnto the Liuer to be better ſtrained; and the reſt being good for nothing, hee doth caſt out through the expulſiue parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Liuer.</head>
                  <p>THen the Liuer (when hee hath thus receiued the beſt and pureſt part of the meate, not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2139:15"/>being contented with the former purging and cleanſing) doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a freſh, ſtrayning it through more narrow paſſages, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better purged and ſeuered, the droſſe and ſlimie part thereof, the Splene doth drawe vnto him for his nutriment, and that which through ouer-much boyling, is turned into a chollericke nature, is ſent vnto the gall or bladder, wherein choller is contained and kept; an other part thereof, which being ouer-thin, will ſerue for no nutriment, the bladder appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for vrine, doth receiue it, and caſt it out as ſuperfluous; the reſt being thus thoroughly purified, is made like vnto bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The great hollowe vaine called</hi> Vena caua.</head>
                  <p>WHen the Liuer hath thus turned it into bloud, it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2139:16"/>conueyed into a great hollowe veine, from whence being caried by other ſmall veines vnto euery part of the body, it ſerueth for the nouriſhing of the whole body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Veines.</head>
                  <p>THe Veins (wherin the bloud is carried to the nouriſhing of euery part of the body) are made of a very fine and thin ryne of skinne, the Pores whereof are couered as it were with a ſpungie matter: for as bloud being groſſe muſt haue the greater Pores to paſſe forth: ſo again leaſt it ſhould runne out altogether at once, and that it might feed and moyſten the parts adioyning by litle and litle, as neceſſitie requireth, God hath couered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſubſtance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2139:16"/>
                  <head>The Arteries.</head>
                  <p>THe Arteries (for that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſpirit which is carried in them, is ſo thinne, that it will paſſe away through very ſmall holes, and can hardly bee kept in) are not made of one, but of two skinnes, and thoſe are very faſt and thicke, that it cannot breake forth.</p>
                  <p>Againe, God hath compaſſed the Veines with Arteries, that the bloud beeing ſtirred with the moouing of the warme ſpirite might runne the more eaſily, whereas otherwiſe by ſtanding ſtill it would congeale and waxe ſtiffe.</p>
                  <p>And therefore in certaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they are ioyned and knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with very fine Pores, that the bloud there-through may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2139:17"/>receiue a litle of the ſpirit, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to further his motion; and the ſpirit on the other ſide (beeing ſomewhat moyſtned with the humour of the bloud) is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from being dried vp.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſtature of man.</head>
                  <p>MAn onely among all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is made to go ſtraight vpright, and vpon two feete one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereas all other goe groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Legges.</head>
                  <p>THe Legs conſiſt of the parts knit together with ioynts, whereof one part is ioyned to the hippe, an other to the knee, and the third part to the ankle, with very ſtrong ſinewes and muſcles, for the readie moouing of them. Againe, thoſe ſinewes and bands,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2139:17"/>are neither too looſe, nor too ſtraight, for being ouer-ſtraight, as the parts could hardly, or not at all be mooued: So if they were ouer looſe, they would not tarry, but fall out of ioynt. And thus through the great benefit of Gods Prouidence, man is able to goe, run, ſtand, and ſit, when he lift.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Buttockes.</head>
                  <p>FOr that it would be hard to ſit vpon that hard bone, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ioynt, God hath giuen man Buttockes, as it were a pillowe, or quiſhion to ſit vpon, by the meanes whereof hee is able to ſit on the bare ground, yea vpon an hard ſtone without any griefe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Backe bone.</head>
                  <p>THe Back bone taking his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at <hi>Os ſacrum,</hi> dooth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2139:18"/>runne vp into the necke, and is as it were a ſtrong piller, ſuſtaining and holding vp the belly, ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, hands, necke, and the head.</p>
                  <p>Againe, this bone beeing hard and full of knobs, is not placed in the forepart of the body (leaſt it ſhould hinder or hurt the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie extenſion of the belly, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and lunges, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in meate, or breath) but in the hinder part as it were a prop or ſtay.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it is not one whole bone, but conſiſts of many ioynts, that with the more eaſe a man might turne and winde his body euery way.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, it is by the Prouidence of God fedde with certaine mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, comming from the braine.</p>
                  <p>The necke may wel be likened to the ceſterne in a Conduit, in the ſides whereof many holes are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2139:18"/>ſtricken, whereby the water (that was brought thither in a great pipe) is ſent forth to diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe the necke reaching downe to the mouth of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, doth ſend the meate and drinke into the belly. It hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the windpipe, which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth from the lunges to the top of the throate; there are veines al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and arteries in it, which carrie bloud and ſpirit vp to feede the braine.</p>
                  <p>The braine alſo dooth ſend downe the marrow through the necke into the backe bone, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough certaine bones adioyning vnto it, wih which marrowe the bones are nouriſhed, and wherof the ſinewes ſpring, which binde the ioynts together, and the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles take their motiue power.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2139:19"/>
                  <head>The head and braine.</head>
                  <p>THe head is placed vpon the height of the body, as it were a Caſtle vpon the toppe of a great hill, wherein the braine (mans eſpeciall treaſure) is kept, as in a very ſtrong hold. The skull is as it were an helmet, compaſſing the braine, &amp; defending it from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde force, which otherwiſe would ſoone receiue great hurt.</p>
                  <p>Againe, leaſt the braine which is ſoft and tender, ſhould be hurt with the hard &amp; ſtiffe bones, God hath encloſed with two coates of skin; whereof one, which is next the braine and dooth encloſe it, is very thinne and ſoft, the other is a more ſtiffe and tough skin (being placed betwixt the brain and the skull) neither ouer-hard for hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the braine, nor yet ouer-thin
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2139:19"/>leaſt the skull through his hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhould hurt or fret it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Eyes.</head>
                  <p>THe Eyes are placed in the Head, as watchmen in the top of a Tower; and to the intent they ſhould watch on both ſides, God hath ſet there not one alone, but two eyes; one towards the right hand, the other to the left.</p>
                  <p>Againe, for that they watching for the ſafegard of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, had need of ſome bulwarke to defend them, God hath placed the browes (hanging ouer them) that both they ſerue for a defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and are a meanes to make vs ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the further off.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, (the browes ſeruing for a pendant houſe to caſt off the wet) God hath ſet fine haires in the vtter parte thereof, which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2139:20"/>enclining towards the temples, do receiue the ſwette falling from the forhead, and carry it from the Eyes (as hurtful vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) downe by the vtter ſide of the face.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, for that theſe watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had need of harnis and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, God hath alſo armed them with their lids, and certain haires in them, as it were ſpeares to keep out litle gnats, moates, duſt, and ſuch like, which would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe flie into the eyes, and hurt them.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, theſe haires be not croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked (as the other vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the brows) leaſt they ſhould runne into the eyes, and hurt them: neither doo they runne ſtraight downeward, for ſo would one ruffle &amp; weare another, through the often clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and twinckling of the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids: but they are ſet ſomewhat a ſlope, and runne outward, ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2139:20"/>that they neither hinder one an other in the ſhutting, and ſerue for the better defence of the Eyes.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, all things in the eye are wonderfull, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et out the great Prouidence of God. viz. The ſmalneſſe of the ſight, the garland about it much like the Rainbow, of diuers colours, the circle like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto horne: the chriſtall ſpheare and glaſſie humour about it: his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouble coate, one coloured like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> grapes, the other in forme like a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſhers net: his ſeate full of ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells: his nutriment which is bought from the braine in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thinne veſſell: and the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it in expelling the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous humours at the corners of the Eye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2139:21"/>
                  <head>The Blood.</head>
                  <p>THe meat being receiued into the Belly, this Iuice is firſt aſſi miled to the Belly, and made white, then being ſent vp to the liuer, it is there turned into blood; afterward, part of it being ſent vp to the braine, it is made white a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and is turned ſome into bones, and otherſome into tough and hard ſinewes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſence of Smelling, and his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrument.</head>
                  <p>THe ſence of Smelling doon diſcerne betwixt ſauours, d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lighting in that which is pleaſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and repelling that which is vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory, as a thing hurtful to nature.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe through that inſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is the head purged of certain
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2139:21"/>excrements. For the head being placed in the higheſt part of the bodie, all the vapours doo aſcend vp thither, which being hurtfull to the brain, are expelled thorow certaine ſpungie holes and pipes. And that theſe moiſt &amp; clammie excrements may with more eaſe and ſpeed be carried away, God hath appointed 2. waies to purge them, that is through the roofe of the mouth, and the noſtrils.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſence of Hearing.</head>
                  <p>THis ſence doth diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſounds, delighting in a pleaſant harmony, and loathing the contrary. By the means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alſo wee attaine to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the liberall Sciences, and of the will of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2139:22"/>
                  <head>The Hands and Armes.</head>
                  <p>THey are neither longer nor ſhotter then is needfull, but are of a iuſt length, and framed to the performing of thoſe workes wherevnto they were ordained. The Arme is diuided into three parts, whereof one part is ioyned to the ſhoulder, another to the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, and the third to the wreſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Fingers.</head>
                  <p>THe Fingers conſiſt of three ioynts, or peeces, the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities whereof are ſome hollow, denting inward, other ſome are round like vnto a ſpheare, the which round endes beeing as it were grafted in the hollow ends: they are bounde together with ſtrong ſinowes, and by the helpe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2139:22"/>of certaine muſcles they are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, where alſo, leaſt their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhould hinder the cloſing of the Fingers, God hath couered them with a thin and ſoft skin or coate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Nayles.</head>
                  <p>THe nailes ſeruing for to keep the ends of the fingers from hurt, are made thin and light for hurting the ſoft fleſh that is vnder them: broad, that they might the better helpe and ſuſtaine the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, being preſſed with any bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Thirdly, they are as it were round, which force is ſtrongeſt for defence, and ſhall leaſt hurt with preſſing the fleſhe vnder it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2139:23"/>
                  <head>The Feete.</head>
                  <p>THe Feet are not made round like an hoofe, nor hard, but ſoft, and ſtretched out in length; wherby, and through the flexible compoſition of the toes, man is able to ſtand the more ſure, and moue with the more eaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The great vſe of the Hands.</head>
                  <p>MAn only hath Hands, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he doth plough, ſowe, plant, reape, threſh, gather in, &amp;c. with infinit workes moe, ſeruing both to pleaſure and neceſſitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Shippe.</head>
                  <p>THe Ship (being made with the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of man) is as it were the Sea waine, or chariot, where the maſt ſerueth in ſtead of the beame, or draught tree, whereon the yokes hang: the ſailes are the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2139:23"/>yokes: and the winde as it were the horſes, and mules to drawe it, which by certaine cordes are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, as it were with bow yokes to draw euen together. Again the ſtern is, as it were the bit or rains, which the Pilot taking in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doth guide the ſhip, ſitting in the hinder part, as it were in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of a waine, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot. And with this ſterne he doth guide the ſhip, not only whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the weather is calme, but is able ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to break the force alſo of the boiſtrous ſtormes, and as it were with a bit, to bridle and hold in thoſe rough and vntamed horſes, which all is wrought and much greater things, our handes being the meanes and inſtruments.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Arts are as it were allyed to the mutuall helpe one of an other.</head>
               <p>THe Carpenter receiueth his tooles of the Smyth, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2139:24"/>Smyth againe hath of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter his houſe. The husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth miniſter foode to them both, but yet hee is compelled to borrow of them both, his houſe, and other inſtruments neceſſary to till his ground, &amp;c. All which are made with the hands of man.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Prouidence of God in teaching man the neceſſary vſe of Mettalls.</head>
                  <p>FOr man himſelfe could neuer haue found out this treaſure ſo deeply laid vp, and hid in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of the earth, or hauing fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it, who elſe could teach him to know the vaines of ſiluer &amp; gold? who taught him to know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the glaſſe? and ſo skilfully to diſcerne the ſame, as to know which ſand ſhould be tryed by fire, and after what ſort, and how long it ſhould lye there?</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2139:24"/>
                  <p>To be ſhort, God alone hath opened theſe vnto man, as alſo how (by the help of fire &amp; breath, or winde) to make thereof ſuch diuers kindes of veſſels to all pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, wherein alſo the notable and neceſſary vſe of the handes may eaſily be ſeene.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Silke-worme.</head>
                  <p>LEaſt man ſhould be puft vp (by reaſon of his great skill, and cunning in ſo many Artes) and wax ouer proud in himſelfe, God hath ſhewed by this little Worme (which draweth a finer thred then man is able) that it is the onely gift and goodneſſe of GOD; which Woorme (as it ſerueth to beate downe the pride of man) doth declare alſo the great Prouidence and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of GOD towardes vs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2139:25"/>whileſt both ſhe, and her whole labours are at the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Phiſicke.</head>
                  <p>WHereas man being mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, is ſubiect to diuers diſeaſes, God hath giuen him this knowledge, both to preſerue health, and to remoue ſickneſſes: In ſo much that Art hath inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted medicines for euery diſeaſe. The earth alſo doth bring foorth diuers kinds of hearbes, whereof ſome are foode for man, other ſome for cattell, and another ſort for medicines. So that oftentimes of thoſe hearbes, which if they ſhould be eaten would kil a man, is made a medicine to remooue ſickneſſes, and to cure the bodie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Grammers.</head>
                  <p>THrough the helpe of this ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (which teacheth both to ſpeak and write) many bookes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2139:25"/>are written very neceſſary for the vſe of man, both concerning the myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, and diuers other needfull Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by the meanes whereof man is able to talk alſo with them that bee abſent: For although the tongue (which is the inſtrument of ſpeech) be ſilent, the right hand taking the pen, doeth commit to writing whatſoeuer we haue to do, or would communicate with our friend, although he be neuer ſo far from vs, And thus the hand (not onely the mouth &amp; tongue) is made the chariot to carry our ſpeech.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The apt placing of the Fingers.</head>
                  <p>THe hand being diuided into fiue Fingers, the thombe is oppoſed, &amp; ſet againſt the foure, bending the contrary way, and as it were claſping the reſt: wherby man is apt to take any thing the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2139:26"/>more readily, and to hold it the faſter, and more ſurely.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prouidence, in that God hath giuen to man the rule and dominion ouer all brute beaſts.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Bee.</head>
                  <p>THe Bees of all creatures doo liue the moſt orderly, &amp; keep lawes moſt duly.</p>
                  <p>Firſt they take their flight out of the hiues orderly, &amp; by courſe, and lighting vpon hearbes, trees, &amp; flowers, do gather out of them that which is for their vſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with being loaden, their former feete ſeruing in ſteed of hands to laie it on their neckes, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe into their hiues.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they build theyr combes (without the helpe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2139:26"/>rule to direct them) in ſo good a proportion and order, with the corners ſo euen and coequall one to another, that he, which is moſt cunning in the Mathematicall ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, is not able to do the like, or come nearer vnto it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, they liue a moſt polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike life, where nothing is priuate, or proper to one, but the treaſure is common to all, whereby there is no ſtrife, or iniurie amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>And to conclude, they haue the beſt kinde of gouernement, whileſt they haue but one, as it were a king to rule them, vnto whom alſo they yeeld a willing and dutifull obedience.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>What man hath to learne of the Bee.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt man ought to learne of the Bee to abhorre idleneſſe, and idle perſons.</p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2139:27"/>
                     <p>Secondly, with a readie and chearfull mind to labor in his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, to gather his goods with painfulneſſe, not iniuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, for the flowers are not the worſe by the Bee, to any vſe or purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, not to ſeeke ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly after honour, and principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, if he be called to any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to rule with right &amp; equitie.</p>
                     <p>Sixtly and laſt of all, not vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to hourd vp their riches, but charitably to impart to ſuch as ſtand in need.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Spider.</head>
                  <p>THe Spider in drawing ſo fine a thred, and weauing his web ſo artificially, hath taught man to make Nets, and ſo conſequently the skil of hunting, fowling, and fiſhing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2139:27"/>
                  <head>Of the Oxe, the Horſe, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant.</head>
                  <p>HErein is the Prouidence of God toward man notably declared, in that he hath ſubdued theſe beaſts (which in ſtrength do farre excell Man) &amp; cauſed them to ſubmit their necks and backes, &amp; to imploy their whole ſtrength to the vſe &amp; ſeruice of man; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as man hath to acknowledge with thankfulnes the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God; ſo muſt he learn ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to obey God, by whoſe means they are ſubdued vnto him. Not only theſe, but all other beaſtes whatſoeuer are ſubiect vnto man, whileſt they ſerue either to feede or cloath him, or els to carry bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or for ſome other neceſſary vſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The cauſe wherefore wilde beaſts and Serpents were created.</head>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2139:28"/>
                  <p>WHeras ſome beaſts do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt man (others beeing eaſily ſubdued) it dooth manifeſtly appeare, that they are not naturally ſubiect, but by the commaundement of God, which only doth keep in the reſt, that they doo not likewiſe breake out and rebell.</p>
                  <p>Againe, God hath created ſome altogether enemies vnto man, to ſuppreſſe, and bridle as it were his inſolencie, and to traine him vp in Vertue, that the terror of thoſe beaſts might teach him to knowe howe needfull the helpe of God is, and ſo to exerciſe himſelfe in prayer, and dutifully to obey GOD, by whoſe onely helpe hee is defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>So that this feare, is as it were a guide to bring man vnto God. And leaſt man beeing continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2139:28"/>in feare of them, ſhould liue a troubleſome and vnpleaſaunt life, GOD hath ſtriken thoſe venemous beaſts with a naturall feare of man, that they hide them ſelues in Caues and holes vnder the grounde, and hath ſo bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their furie, that they hurt but ſeldome times, and that in their owne defence, when they are by men hurt, or prouoked therevnto.</p>
                  <p>As for the wilde beaſtes, he hath ſent them into the woods, craggie Rockes and Dennes in the Wilderneſſe, to dwell farre from the companie of man, and hath ſet them theyr appoynted time, (the night when man is at reſt, and ſafe) to ſeeke their praie.</p>
                  <p>So that the wilde beaſtes and venemous ſerpents, are as it were
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2139:29"/>whips and rods for children, and ſuch as are not throughly inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the feare and loue of God; but as for men, and ſuch as are ſtrong in faith, they are without any feare of them, as did appeare by <hi>Noah, Daniel, Paul,</hi> and many moe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Riches and Pouertie, are both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for man.</head>
               <p>WHereas the enemies here take occaſion to blaſpheme God, &amp; ſay that there is no Prouidence in him, nor care of man, becauſe they ſee the wicked abound in wealth, and liue in all kinde of pleaſures, the godly man contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe through the oppreſſion of the rich, to liue in great pouertie, and very miſerably: they ought rather to conclude, and that more truly (bridling this raſh iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; learning to reforme their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errour) that riches cannot
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2139:29"/>therefore be the true felicitie and happines (as they dreame) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vertue is thus by their own te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie ſuppreſſed, neither that Pouertie is miſerie, ſeeing that godly men, and ſuch as excell in vertue, doo oftentimes liue in want and neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſeeing they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge vertue to be the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iewell, and ſuch as doo moſt feruently imbrace &amp; follow her, to liue a moſt happie life, there is no cauſe why they ſhould extoll riches, as to thinke them the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly note of true happineſſe, which they ſee commonly with theyr eyes, to be the greateſt enemy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vertue.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Vertues, what they are, and firſt of Prudence.</head>
                  <p>PRude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is as it wer the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and care of the mind, or reaſon, wherwith man is endued;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2139:30"/>As fooliſhneſſe and lacke of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight (which is contrary to <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>) is a drunkenneſſe, which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of affections, doth darken and blinde the reaſon and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of man, not ſuffring him to foreſee that which is profitable and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for him; The cure whereof, and health of the mind, is called <hi>Prudence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Temperance.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TEmperance</hi> is a right conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde, when the rude and diſordered deſires ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are brideled, and ruled by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Fortitude.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FOrtitude</hi> is that whereby a man is ſtirred vp vnto a lawfull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and iuſt reuenge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Iuſtice.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IVſtice</hi> is a lawfull and right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the mind, wherby
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2139:30"/>the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſubiect vnto her, are ruled and directed.</p>
                     <p>The affections of Luſt &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſubmitting themſelues vnto reaſon, and being ruled thereby through a mutual qualifying one of another, do abſolue, and make this notable vertue of <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Riches and great aboundance, is an enemie vnto vertue.</head>
                  <p>THe great troubles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall cares, which follow the getting and poſſeſſing of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the infinite toſſing and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyling of thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue them, (whileſt they are neuer at reſt), cannot accorde with the quiet and peaceable ſtate of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but are enemies that hurt and hinder the good courſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2139:31"/>
                  <p>Secondly, he that is giuen alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither to ſerue the belly, in eating &amp; drinking, deſiring daintie fare, and delighting in great diuerſitie of meates &amp; drinks (which faults and many moe, accompany ſuch as abounde in wealth) how is it poſſible that he ſhould liue a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and contented life?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, hee that doeth thus quench the watchfulneſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſet on fire the affections, bringeth reaſon into ſeruitude, and make her a ſeruaunt vnto the belly, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath ſet as ladie and miſtris ouer all the bodie: he that deliuereth the prince as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner vnto his ſubiects, &amp; caſteth the gouernor of the chariot to be torne in peeces of his horſes: He (I ſay) that will not ſuffer the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to hold the ſterne any longer, and to guide the ſhip, but will let it be carried headlong with the ſtormes of theſe tempeſtuous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2139:31"/>and ſo to be drowned in waues: Hee is not onely vtterly voyd of wit &amp; wiſdome, but hath abandoned &amp; giuen himſelf ouer to all kind of Intemperancie and filthie pleaſures.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, in great abundance there is ſmall hope of iuſtice, for he that is greedily bent to heape vp great riches, doth make no difference betweene right &amp; wrong. So that riches is an enemie to euery kind of vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pouertie is a great helper, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer vnto vertue.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt the want of things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doth compell the affections to be ſubiect to reaſon, and will not ſuffer them to ſwell vp, or to ſtriue againſt their ladie &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as it falleth out oftentimes in ſuch as are wantonly brought vp, and delight in belly cheare.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the mind therby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuered from ſuperfluous
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2139:32"/>troubles, and voyde of outward cares, dooth enioy great reſt and quietneſſe: So that looking into her ſelfe, ſhee dooth beholde her own dignitie, and taking the rule into her handes, dooth preſcribe vnto her ſubiects, lawes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and order, and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or puniſhing the rebellious affections of Luſt and Anger (the one by the other), dooth bring them into order.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the great labour and trauel (wherevnto Pouertie dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth man) doth much profite to bridle &amp; keep vnder the outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous luſts, for it doth conſume and ſpend that matter wherwith they are fed, ſo as they are not able to breake forth.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, the examples of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; vertuous men in all ages fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning dooth manifeſtly declare, that pouertie doth furder more to the obteining of vertue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2139:32"/>and riches. In ſo much that many (as <hi>Socrates, Diogenes, Anaxarchus</hi> and others, for the loue they bare to vertue, and that they might the better attaine vnto it, did giue and caſt away their riches, and all that they had, chuſing rather, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to liue in voluntarie Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Riches are not ill of themſelues, but through the abuſe of men.</head>
                  <p>RIches, for that they come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God are not il in themſelues, but are giuen as neceſſary inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to make &amp; poliſh the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Image of vertue: which if man ſhall contrariwiſe abuſe to the making of an Image of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, the Inſtrument is not to be blamed, which was to be wel vſed, but the man which hath wickedly abuſed the ſame. As Iron and Wine although they be diuerſe times abuſed to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and drunkenneſſe, are not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2139:33"/>to be caſt away, and condemned as ſuperfluous, but are kept not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as verie neceſſarie, &amp; commended as great bleſſings of God: Euen ſo riches are not therefore to be blamed, becauſe wicked men abuſe them, but to be acknowledged as the gifts of God, neceſſarie for many good purpoſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Why God hath not giuen riches to euery man.</head>
                  <p>AS God hath not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of the bodie the like operation, but to euerie one a peculiar function, as the eye to diſcern colours, the eare to iudge the difference of ſoundes, and ſo forth in all the reſt, that through the varietie of their operations, &amp; the mutual help that they haue one of another, the bodie ſhould want nothing neceſſary, and that amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the members there ſhould be no grudge, or enuy, whileſt no
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2139:33"/>one part can iuſtly ſay vnto another (I haue no need of thee): Euen ſo hath not God made all rich alike, but ſome poore, that one ſtanding in need of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, through their mutuall helpe; this his Common-wealth might be preſerued; which otherwiſe would be quite ouerthrowne: whileſt euerie man abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in wealth, there wold be found none to ſow, plow, or to do any ſuch inferior &amp; neceſſary works. Whereby one of theſe two inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences would followe of neceſſitie, that euery man muſt learne all Artes, and do all workes himſelfe, (which thing is vnpoſſible) or elſe that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould periſh together for want of things neceſſary (which were abſurd and lamentable). So that in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie alſo the Prouidence of God doth notably appeare.</p>
                  <p>The ſtate &amp; condition of the Rich and Poore, is naturally alike, and all one.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, all men, both rich &amp; poore,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2139:34"/>haue one and the ſelfe ſame earth for their houſe, nurſe, mother, and graue, alike common to euery one.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Sunne, Moone, and Starres, giue their light indifferently to all, neither is the Aire peculiar vnto the rich, but all breathe of it alike.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The bodies likewiſe both of rich and poore are alike, but that the poore man hath (for the moſt part) the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and more healthfull bodie. For (as a wiſe Phyſitian ſaide) Scarcitie &amp; Lack is the mother of good health, to the preſeruation whereof, Exerciſe alſo, and Labour, is of great force, and helpeth much.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The ſoules in them, are both of like nature.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 They haue one beginning of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are brought forth with paine alike. But that the poore women (commonly) are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with more eaſe: For through continuall labor, her childbirth is the leſſe painfull.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:2139:34"/>
                  <p>Againe, comming into the world, nature hath not cloathed the riche mans childe better then the poore mans, but they are broght forth both alike naked, and fed with milke alike.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 And as they had one entrance into the world, ſo doo they depart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: for death is common vnto both, and hath no reſpect of perſons, but ſtriketh in differently.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 After death alſo they do both of the in putrifie and rot, the like matter and corruption iſſueth out of them, and together they become wormes meate. So that in all or the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, the condition of the rich and poore are both alike.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How Riches and Pouertie are common vnto all men.</head>
                  <p>GOD hath ſo ordained Pouertie, with all kinde of Artes, that the Rich and wealthie are compelled to bring theyr money vnto the poore man, and to buye of him all thing,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2139:35"/>whereof they ſtand in need, without whoſe helpe they are not able to liue, notwithſtanding their great wealth. Wherein we are to acknowledge the great wiſedome and Prouidence of God, who hath giuen riches vnto ſome, and to other knowledge in arts and ſciences, that through this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie (where they ſtand in ſo great need one of another) they might be knit together in mutuall concord and friendſhip. For as the Rich men doo ſtand in need of Poore Artificers, to ſupply their neceſſary wants: ſo again the poore men are ſet on worke with the rich mens money. So that both of them ſtanding in neede (the one of wares, the other of money) doo ſhew how Riches and Pouertie are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnto all men, and both verie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>God hath not giuen Riches to good men onely.</head>
                  <p>GOD hath not beſtowed Riches onely vpon good men, leaſt the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2139:35"/>enemie ſhould accuſe God not to deale with indifferencie, or ſlaunder the godly, that they ſhould loue God onely in reſpect of theſe bleſſings, and for feare of looſing the ſame. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath diſtributed riches &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie indifferently vnto both, &amp; hath ordained them, as certain inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or matter to worke withall, which the godly vſing to the attaining of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the vngodly abuſing vnto vice, there is no excuſe left, or hope of pardon for ſuch as ſpend their liues in wickednes, whether they be rich or poore. For they which get their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches well, and honeſtly, and doo not encreaſe them with other mens hurt &amp; miſerie, but vſe them to the reliefe of ſuch as ſtand in need, do iuſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe &amp; condemne the couetous and vngodly rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: As the poore man, which tempereth his pouertie with the ſtudie of wiſedom, and ſuſtaineth the rage thereof with a ſtout and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant minde, doth condemne the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2139:36"/>life of ſuch as beeing poore, doe ſpend their dayes altogether in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The poore are commonly more health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then the rich.</head>
                  <p>WHerin the care &amp; Prouidence of God dooth notably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, in that foreſeeing the diuerſe helpes and remedies that ſuch as bee wealthy are able to prouide, which the poore man by reaſon of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie cannot do, he hath as it were, allotted vnto the poore man a more ſtrong and healthfull body; ſo that health doth recompence the want of wealth: and oftentimes it falleth out, that the rich man wiſheth the poore mans health, when the poore man will not chaunge his ſtate for all the rich mans wealth.</p>
                  <p>Againe, in ſickneſſes you ſhall ſee the poore man who lyeth on the bare ground without bedde or matte, to take his griefe more quietly, and haue leſſe paine then the rich, which lie
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2139:36"/>in beddes of Downe, and haue all kindes of Phiſicke to mittigate their paine. So gracious is God in proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for theſe, which through want are not able to prouide for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the difference in the eſtates of men (whereof ſome obey, and other commaund) is very neceſſary.</head>
               <p>GOd in the beginning made but one man of the earth (for the woman was made of a bone taken out of <hi>Adam</hi>) leaſt through the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of earth ſhe ſhould bee thought to be of an other nature. Of which couple ſproong all mankind. So that in the beginning there was no ſuch difference of Lordes and Seruants. Neyther in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> (when hee, and his wife, his three ſonnes, and their wiues, entered into the Arke) doo wee read that any Seruant went in, or find this name of Seruant:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2139:37"/>for as then was not this diſtinction of degrees inſtituted, or thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie. But afterward when it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that much miſchiefe did riſe through ouer-much libertie, whileſt there was no magiſtrate to bridle the outragious multitude, Lawes were deuiſed, which being found to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie neceſſary; it was alſo as neceſſary that there ſhould be Law-makers, and magiſtrates to execute &amp; put the ſame in practiſe: which could not poſſibly be, (this equalitie among all men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtill. And therefore it was needfull that there ſhould be this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of magiſtrates and ſubiects: for God ſeeing that by ſin there was brought in a wonderfull diſorder and confuſion of all things, did preſcribe an order in ſetting downe Lawes to ſuppreſſe and bridle the rage thereof, the raines whereof he hath deliuered into the handes of the magiſtrate, to put the ſame in practiſe: wherevpon ariſeth this neceſſarie diſtinction of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2139:37"/>maiſters and ſeruants; Magiſtrates to commaund, and inferior ſubiects to obey.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Seruitude is very profitable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</head>
                  <p>AS in a ſhip, the good order is the preſeruation of ſuch as ſaile ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whileſt ſome doo rowe, otherſome do make fit the Cables, others are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied about other thinges neceſſarie, which they are commaunded to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: and the guide in the fore ende of the ſhip, doth diſcrie the Rockes, quickſands, and ſhelues, giuing war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the maiſter, who holding the ſterne doth direct the ſhip, and hath the rule &amp; authoritie ouer all the reſt, whoſe commandement they do rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obey, whereby they are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſaile without feare, or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which could not be, if euery man ſhould be occupied about one, and the ſelfe ſame thing, or without order do euery man what he thought beſt: So likewiſe in a houſe where diuers
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2139:38"/>workes are to be done, which require the help of many men, if there ſhould be no one man to rule &amp; commaund the reſt, but that euery man might do what he liſt, it were vnpoſſible for any familie to conſiſt or ſtand. So that it is verie neceſſary, that there be both Maiſters and Seruants.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Seruant hath a more pleaſant life then the Maiſter of the houſe.</head>
                  <p>WHereas ſome thinke it a ſore and greeuous thing to ſerue, and beeing wearied with continuall labour, to take his portion meaſured out as his Maiſter ſhall thinke good; if they will diligently conſider all things, and looke thoroughly into both their eſtates, they ſhall find the Seruaunt to liue the more pleaſaunt life. For although hee be in bondage of bodie, yet is his minde free, and voyd of many cares wherewith the Maiſter is greatly ouer-charged.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:2139:38"/>
                  <p>Dearth &amp; ſcarcitie doth neuer breake his ſleepe, he neuer taketh care how to ſell his commodities, or is grieued when they lie vpon his hands and waxe cheape, neither ſtandeth hee in any feare of his Creditors, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thought how to diſcharge out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payments, and to maintaine his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. He dare meete a Sergiant in the teeth, and is not afraide of the frowning countenance of the Iudge, but without all care of minde, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his meate with a good ſtomacke, ſleepeth ſoundlye, and is in good health; wheras the maiſter with theſe, and many moe cares is ſo vexed and tormented continually, that he can neither eate his meate quietly in the day time, nor take any reſt in the night, but paſſeth his time in great care, and ſmall pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſeeing the Maiſter dooth oftentimes labour as painfully, as any Seruaunt, but the Seruants are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2139:39"/>troubled with no care like vnto the maiſter, there is no cauſe why they ſhould bee thought miſerable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their labours (which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to their maiſters with them) but great cauſe, why they may be ſaid to liue more pleaſantly, as that they are voyd of all care of minde, wherewith the maiſter is oftentimes ſpent &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ill Magiſtrates and Maiſters.</head>
                  <p>THeſe men haue not their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie from God, but the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſuch as be ſubiect hath drawne the ſame vpon them. For when they would reape no profit by ſuch as ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led well and honeſtly, but through their lewd behauiour contumeliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did caſt off their diſcipline, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued themſelues of the Prouidence of God, through wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and direction they haue receiued theſe wicked Princes &amp; Magiſtrates, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the ill gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> might remember
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2139:39"/>the other, and learne how neceſſary it is to haue, and obey, honeſt and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouernors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſeruants which haue a ſound and goodminde, are not hurt by ſeruing of ill maiſters.</head>
                  <p>MAny ſeruants haue beene found to bee great louers of Vertue, which ſerued with a readie and good mind, doing that which was their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not compelled, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heart, and haue had a great care of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: whereby they haue not onely obtained liberty from their bondage, but haue gotten great wealth and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, as rewards for their good &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice.</p>
                  <p>So that ſeruice is no hinderance to the attaining of vertue or wealth. As may appeare by <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruaunt, and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> with many moe. Whereof the one (beeing ſent by <hi>Abraham</hi> his Maiſter to chooſe a wife for <hi>Iſaac</hi> his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2139:40"/>ſonne) is ſet foorth as a patterne of a faithfull Seruant, and one that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God. And <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by ſeruitude at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to greater wealth and honour then his brethren, who neuer ſerued, but were alwaies at freedome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The wickednes of the Maiſter, cannot hurt a godly Seruant.</head>
                  <p>AS may appeare in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whoſe godly and chaſte mind (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allurements, faire promiſes, and great daunger in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling his Miſtreſſe vnlawfull luſts) was not corrupted or defiled, but continued ſound and conſtant in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Likewiſe <hi>Abdias,</hi> Seruant vnto wicked <hi>Achab,</hi> and curſed <hi>Iezabel,</hi> who ſought the vtter deſtruction of all the ſeruaunts &amp; Prophets of God) did preſerue from death, and nouriſh an hundreth Prophets, whom he hid an two Caues, notwithſtanding the brutiſh crueltie of his Lord; Neither
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2139:40"/>did the great famine and dearth of victualls (which was exceeding ſore at that time, by reaſon that it rained not in three yeares, and ſix moneths) any whit ſlacke his care in prouiding all things neceſſary for them.</p>
                  <p>Againe, in the time of <hi>Zedechias,</hi> the laſt king of the Iewes, who would not giue eare vnto the words of the Lord, but caſt the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deepe and ſtinking dungeon, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimelech</hi> one of the kings ſeruaunts, an Ethiopian, and an Eunuch, not regarding the wickednes which raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Court, and the great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred which was conceiued againſt the Prophet, nor once calling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce his owne ſeruile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and ſtate, went boldly vnto the King, and reprooued his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt ſentence and crueltie againſt the Prophet of God, mouing him with godlie perſwaſions to take <hi>Ieremie</hi> out of the Dungeon, which beeing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2139:41"/>obtained, this <hi>Eunuch</hi> was aduanced, and did miniſter all things neceſſary during the whole time of the ſiege, when the Iewes were led captiues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Babylon,</hi> by <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> the king.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Daniel, Ananias, Azarias,</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zael,</hi> though they were led captiues into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and liued in bondage vnder a moſt wicked king, yet could they not be brought to tranſgreſſe the lawes of the liuing God in any point, either for deſire of life, or feare of death, or any torments whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore let no man condemne ſeruitude as euill, or thinke that the wickedneſſe of the maiſter can ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the vertue of a good and godly ſeruant, if he haue a mind well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but in all things let him confeſſe, and acknowledge the Prouidence of God. For by theſe examples it doth appeare plainly, that a ſeruant may be vertuous &amp; godly, though his maiſter be neuer ſo vicious and vngodly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2139:41"/>
                  <head>Why doth God ſuffer the godly to be led into captiuitie?</head>
                  <p>GOd hath a care euen ouer thoſe that do offend, and of great loue doth puniſh them; wherefore when he ſuffreth the wicked for their ſinnes to be ledde captiue, hee ſendeth with them alſo good men, as ſchoole-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and teachers, by whoſe good counſell &amp; example they may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in the true and right path.</p>
                  <p>Againe, theſe godly men being in captiuitie, haue not only bin a means of ſaluation vnto their fellowe priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but through their good life and doctrine, haue brought alſo many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels to the light and knowledge of the true God. So that in all his doings God ſheweth himſelfe to haue a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care of man.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:2139:42"/>
               <head>The ſtudie of Righteouſnes is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruite, although in this life it doth not appeare. And of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
               <p>ALthough the godly in this life are commonly oppreſſed with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and ſeruitude, and liue not in like pleaſure &amp; proſperitie as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doo: yet notwithſtanding they haue pleaſures, and great pleaſures. For the godly do not think the praiſe and rewardes of mortall men to be a ſufficient recompence for theyr tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes; and therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temning them, they doo looke for the promiſes of GOD, and attend the comming of their Guide and Captaine, to receiue thoſe crownes of vnſpeakable glory, (rewards from heauen). They wayt for the Reſurrection of their bodies, that being taken vp into heauen, they may ioy with the holie Angels, and haue the continuall and endleſſe frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2139:42"/>of him, for whoſe ſake they haue ſuffered ſo many troubles, which is a moſt excellent reward, and the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true happineſſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſeeing the poſſeſſion of vertue is a moſt precious Iewell, and is not gotten; nor kept without great trouble and paines: it were a great abſurditie, that all other inferior arts and exerciſes ſhould haue theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and Vertue onely be without all recompence.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>There is an Eternall life, where Vertue is rewarded.</head>
                  <p>WHereas God ſuffereth ſome vertuous and godly men in this world, to liue &amp; die without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and in great contempt; Other ſome againe to liue in great honour: It is an euident argument (for that God is iuſt in all his dooings) that there is another life prepared, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they whiche haue doone well,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2139:43"/>ſhall be rewarded accordingly. So that in giuing honor vnto ſome here, he doth manifeſt and declare that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath her crowne &amp; reward; And in ſuffering other, ſome to liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all honour or reward, hee doth ſhew plainly that there is another life, and doth thereby notably confirme the hope of thoſe thinges which are looked for.</p>
                  <p>Againe, if there were no life after this, they which are puniſhed heere might ſeeme to haue great iniurie, ſeeing other committing the like or greater faultes, to receiue no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all. And the vertuous men likewiſe which are not rewarded, as other godly men are, ſhould haue too great cauſe to complaine, and accuſe the iuſtice of God: So that of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie (except we will denie God to be iuſt) there muſt be another iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where ſuch as haue eſcaped puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heere, may ſuffer according to their deſerts; and they which haue
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2139:43"/>receiued heere no reward for their well doing, may be fully rewarded, and recompenced for their great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Reſurrection of the bodie is neceſſary.</head>
                  <p>FOr it were great abſurditie &amp; want of iuſtice, if the ſoule alone, (and not the bodie) ſhould be glorified or tormented, ſeeing the bodie hath bin a great furtherer and ſetter forward, as well of the godly as the wicked o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations of the minde, and an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to performe the ſame. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in iuſtice it is requiſite, and verie neceſſary (ſeeing the bodie hath bene a copartner here with the ſoule, both of her godly labors, and wicked plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures) that it ſhould be raiſed againe, and together with the ſoule receiue due puniſhment, as they haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or like glory, as rewards for their vertuous and godly labours ſuſtained together in this life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:2139:44"/>
                  <head>It is not vnpoſsible for God to raiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the dead bodies.</head>
                  <p>ALl things are poſſible vnto God, and eaſie to be done, (ſeeme they vnto man neuer ſo hard, or vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) for he that made all things with his word, can eaſily gather together the parts of man (although they be deuoured of beaſts, and conſumed into duſt and aſhes) and raiſe him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: As it is much more eaſie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore a thing being decaied, then with his onely word to make all things of nothing, as he did.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How God in times paſt had a care, not onely of the Iewes, but of all men; And of the Incarnation of Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</head>
               <p>NEither the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, nor the earth, the ſea, the Moone, or Starres, neither this whole viſible, and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2139:44"/>creation, do ſo notably declare, and ſet out the exceeding greatneſſe of the goodneſſe and loue of God, as this, that the onely begotten ſonne of God, of like ſubſtance to the Father, tooke the ſhape of a ſeruant vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and was conuerſant here among men on earth, in the ſimilitude and figure of man, that taking vpon him our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and bearing our diſeaſes: he might ſo be our Phyſitian, and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, through whom we haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this notable benefit (by adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to be made the ſonnes of God.</p>
               <p>For God, when he ſaw our reuolting from him, being our Creator, vnto a moſt cruel tyrannie, and how we had wilfully throwne our ſelues into the dungeon of all miſchife, treading the lawes of nature vnder feete; and that theſe viſible creatures could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and bring vs to the obedience of our Creator, it pleaſed him of great mercie to worke our ſaluation ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, in great wiſdome &amp; iuſtice.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:2139:45"/>
               <p>For in the reſtoring of man, God did not vſe his onely power, whereby he was able to do what he would, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet mercy alone, leaſt the enemy of mankind ſhould haue cauſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his dealing, as iniurious, but did deuiſe and take a courſe, wherein he declared both great loue and iuſtice, for vniting vnto himſelfe the captiue nature of man, he brought it into the field to reuenge his former foyle, and did ſo furniſh it with all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that the enemie which in times paſt had preuailed againſt man, was now by man vtterly ouerthrowne; So that his tyrannie being diſſolued, man was by iuſtice deliuered from moſt miſerable ſeruitude, and reſtored to his former libertie, which was the cauſe that Chriſt was borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and tooke fleſh of the virgin.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The cauſe wherefore Chriſt faſted for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes.</head>
                  <p>CHriſt by his faſting, and hunger, did as it were prouoke the enemy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2139:45"/>to a conflict, who perceiuing his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, was in great hope of victorie, and came with a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence as it had bene to deale with <hi>Adam</hi> (whom that way hee did ouerthrow, but (finding vnder <hi>Adams</hi> nature) his Creator) he departed, as confounded.</p>
                  <p>Againe, in faſting hee would not paſſe the number of 40. daies (which faſt both <hi>Moyſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> did performe in times paſt, leaſt men ſhould doubt of the veritie of his humanitie, and hungring, he ſhewed himſelfe to be a man in truth, and not onely in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and appearance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The death of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>HE was nayled on the Croſſe, and ſuffered, not for his ſinnes, but for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man (through tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) had caſt himſelfe in debt, and was not able of himſelfe to paie the ſame: Chriſt taking the nature of man (as it were mony to paie the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) did rule, and guide it with ſo great wiſedome and Iuſtice, that hee
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2139:46"/>ſatisfied the law, and paying the debt did ſet man againe at libertie.</p>
                  <p>For this cauſe hee ſuffered death vpon the Croſſe, (which was by the lawe accurſed, as alſo the nature of man, becauſe it had tranſgreſſed the lawe) that by taking vpon him the curſe, which was common to all, and ſuffering that moſt ſhamefull death vndeſerued, he might deliuer all men from their deſerued condemnation: for though hee was not ſubiect vnto the curſe (as being free from all ſins) yet was hee content to ſuffer death, which was the puniſhment due vnto ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Reſurrection of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>WHen Chriſt had thus broken the bondes of Death, and wrought the ſaluation of man, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned againe into heauen, and by the raiſing and carrying of his owne bodie, did giue as it were an earneſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2139:46"/>or aſſuraunce vnto all the godlie of their reſurrection and aſcention.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>This miſterie of Chriſts Natiuitie and death, was purpoſed from euerlaſting.</head>
                  <p>WHereas ſome curiouſly doo ſeeke to know the vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wiſdome of God, and demaund wherefore God did not worke this from the beginning, but hath let it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlip ſo many thouſand yeres, they are to learne, firſt that it is ouer great preſumption and arrogancie in them, too curiouſly to ſearche out thoſe things which God hath hid, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued vnto himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly (for the thing) it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined long ſince, euen from the beginning, but deferred vntill this time, as moſt fit and conuenient to ſet out his great wiſedome and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2139:47"/>
                  <head>How God had a care of all men, euen from the beginning.</head>
                  <p>IT doth manifeſtly appeare by the whole ſtorie of the olde Teſtament, that God in his Prouidence had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a care of all men, not onely of thoſe which came of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but of all the of ſpring of <hi>Adam.</hi> For by this one people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hee brought all Nations from their Idolatrie to the knowledge of the true God; for in bleſſing their good life with proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and great victories, he did declare his goodneſſe; and as it were allure all men to imbrace their doctrine; and againe in puniſhing their wickednes, and ſuffering them to be led captiues into ſtraunge and farre countries, hee did both ſhewe his iuſtice, and vſed them as meanes to preach and ſet out the glorie of God, and the truth of their doctrine vnto all nations, which if they had remained ſtil in their own
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2139:47"/>country, could not haue bene done ſo plentifully, and effectually.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The preaching of the Goſpell vnto the Gentiles.</head>
                  <p>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great miſterie of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was fulfilled, and the time was come that the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt ought to be publiſhed through the whole world, then did God diſpearſe and ſcatter abroad the remnant of his people (which of his great mercy hee had choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all nations, euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) into all the coaſtes of the earth, that all they which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with the multitude of Gods, might learne that there was but one God, the Creator of heauen &amp; earth: as alſo that the Goſpel (which was to be preached by the holie Apoſtles) might haue the eaſier paſſage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2139:48"/>
                  <head>But how can the Iewes be ſaid to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goſpel, which they did by all meanes withſtand and hinder?</head>
                  <p>THeir incredulitie &amp; ſtubburneſſe did ſo litle hinder the truth of the Goſpell, that it was an occaſion of great confirmation thereof, whileſt thoſe things which they denied, were ſo ſubſtantially prooued by ſo many teſtimonies out of the lawe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that both their errors were vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly confuted, and the Gentiles were notably confirmed in the trueth of Chriſt, whom they ſawe by ſo many Prophets and ſo long ago to be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told. So that God may well be ſaid in all ages, to haue had a great care and Prouidence, not onely of the Iewes, but of all mankind euen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Deo gloria.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2139:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
